hi Michael thanks so much for making
time for this conversation and we've
actually had a couple of conversations
recently that we got so carried away
with that we didn't really hit the
record button but I just would love to
start as I usually do in this series
with rather than me introducing you I
got I've mentioned your work in my book
and I have been excited by by your work
ever since I first found out about it
and and see you as one of the real
pioneers of trying to include biomimetic
thinking but also at the system's level
how do we learn from ecosystems into the
projects you work with in your
architectural firm so um over to you
with how did you get to do the work
you're doing today and tell me a little
bit about you your story yeah well
thanks very much for involving me in
this Daniel it's always a pleasure
talking to you so you know in some ways
it goes back to when I was a teenager
how passionate about three things design
biology in the environment and at that
stage I couldn't see how those things
fit together I thought about studying
biology it's university but I didn't see
there was a creative side to it so I
left that behind studied architecture
and then it was really when I joined
Grimshaw age 32 work on the Eden Project
from the early stages that's when I
realized that there was a way to bring
together those three strands of design
biology in the environment and then my
understanding of the subject moved on in
a really transformative way when I went
on a five-day course at Schumaker
college and that was led by Janine
Benyus and Amory Lovins and I learned
more in those five days than the
previous ten years of going to
conferences and listening to architects
talk about her level and so I I led a
lot of the projects that were pushing
pushing sustainable and regenerative
ideas Grimshaw
and I came to conclusion that I wanted
to set up my own company so that I could
focus exclusively on this area and to
also try a new way of working as an
architect I had a feeling that you know
architects tend to be rather reactive
you generally as an architect you wait
for a client to come along sometimes you
get a very good one as we did on the
Eaton project but more often than not
you get a client that says they want a
sustainable building but then often
they've already chosen the sites which
is not ideal sometimes they've already
got a team that's not ideal and and so
from that point on you're just trying to
make the best out of a compromise and I
felt there an opportunity for a new way
of working there was a bit more like say
where product designer works where you
have an idealized notion of what the
project is you develop it up to a
certain point and then when you know
what he did what it is and what it can
do back into wish you find the client
and by doing that my hope was that we
could overcome some of the obstacles to
to faster progress and there were a
number of projects we did like when I
say we I'm talking about my company
exploration so it's me and quite a range
of colleagues and it's always a
collaborative process I really enjoy
working with a Polymathic team so I'm
not from the school of thought that is
has this of Architects is the sort of
iconic super designer and the rest of
the team is just there to realize the
beautiful vision it's not like that at
all I actually see the role of an
architect much more like Benjamin Zander
talks about the role of a conductor he
says that the conductor doesn't make a
sound but relies instead for his or her
power on making other people powerful
and unifying that into a cohesive result
and so we found we've worked on a number
of projects similar to the process I
described where we initiated them at the
Sahara forest projects is one such
example and back to that and then we've
also worked on projects where we do have
a client from the beginning and and
generally that's been a client that
wants to really go beyond conventional
sustainability when I said that what I
mean is going beyond simply mitigating
negatives we've just seen way too much
of that and in a way we've had kind of
30 years of mitigating negatives and
that it hasn't got us anywhere near to
where we really need to get you so for
instance we did design for an office
building with a client called dr. Ralph
Bell and either a very high-performing
sustainable building and became more and
more interest in the idea of using
biomimicry to go one step further or all
the different aspects of the projects
and we showed how we could achieve a
huge saving in physical resources huge
saving in energy as well as making it a
much better working around for people in
terms of their health and well-being
briefly because what I find
distinguishes you from a lot of other
biomimetic architects is that um when
you when you kind of take the the rule
book of biomimicry there's always this
there's three levels of mimicry you
mimic form process or you do ecosystems
level biomimicry and I feel like you
you're one of the few who really works
on but with biomimicry much more in
terms of patterns of flow and energy and
regulating climate like so many of the
project from the Eden Project and the
Sahara forest project aren't just about
creating a beautiful structure that has
a biomimetic form but they're actually
about increasing the potential in that
place to do things that otherwise that
place might might not be the ideal
location for like regulating climate and
one's for EM homed in on that a little
bit with it I really like the way you
describe it in your book how on earth is
an amazingly complex arrangement of
nested systems there's systems of a
cellular level we are a system as an
organism and as we now know only 10% of
our cells or human cells the rest of
microbial and we have a relationship
with a broader ecosystem and that exists
at local levels regional levels and all
the way up to global levels and of
course with the work of James Lovelock
and Lynn Margulis we know that well with
a reasonable degree of certainty now
that the earth exists as as this amazing
evolved set of interacting systems and
self-regulating system it's interesting
that's no longer considered that
controversial as a scientific idea and
so really the challenge for us in moving
beyond sustainable into regenerative
design as itis here is to see how we can
integrate ourselves into those systems
and it's crucial that we look at the
resource flows of our projects and we
look at the potential of the place
our idea of place that's something that
architects have been interested in for a
long time but it tends to be a cultural
idea of place and the architects that
are good at the cultural aspects of
place tend not to be the same as those
who are good at the ecological aspects
of place and it's time we we did both we
need to we need to really develop a
deeper order understanding of what place
is and how that forms an essential
starting point for the design this is a
this speaks very much to again in my
book I building on John Todd's
definition of ecological design elegant
solutions predicated by the uniqueness
of place I I added the word biocultural
before uniqueness of place and because
of that it's we need to be be finely
attuned to both the the cultural
historical context and the the specific
biophysical specificity of the local
ecosystem very much alignment yeah and
we've used that kind of thinking on a
number of projects more risk than one
than the Sarah Forest project is a
scheme we designed for client in India
for a zero-waste zero-carbon textile
factory and that was really challenging
because textiles as an industry uses
huge quantities of energy with turn and
also those tend not to be particularly
enjoyable working environments and
working with this behind we were able to
show that we could get all the way to
zero carbon and close loop on water zero
solid waste and grace to fantastic
working environment for people and one
very important part of that was using
forms of biological remediation for the
water so we had a water expert and a
green chemist involved and by designing
out all the toxic chemicals to the
system it then made it much more
feasible to use biological forms of
treatment for that water
and very deliberately we put these these
biological treatment ponds all the way
and down the middle of the factory there
were two - you pass the factory and down
the middle they would police have read
bad water treatment systems so we were
actually getting a secondary benefit
because we had big picture windows all
the way down and that meant that from
any part of the factory people look out
and get a view of nature with all the
psychological benefits that that's that
Gibbs as well as in sorry just reminded
me have you come across the work of an
architect Chris Galvin and we used to
work for therapy and terraces bright
green there's because he I think was the
lead on when they wrote a report on the
economics of Biophilia and ensured how
what you just described for the factory
they were mainly looking at hospitals
how you can actually get a financial
benefit in terms of how people work how
quickly their Hospital turns over and
heals people if there's a lot of direct
visual access to life yeah that's the
classic study I think it was the
hospital in Pittsburgh and there was one
award where all of patients were
recovering from the same operation so it
was a perfect controlled experiment off
the beds had a view across our roads to
a blank wall and the other half had a
view to a plant each courtyard with nice
vegetation and so on and the people with
the view of nature recovered eight
percent more quickly and and the really
dramatic difference was how much less
they needed in terms of pain-relieving
drugs fifty percent less family and
quite apart from the amazing human
benefits of that approach I think think
of the economic benefits of treating one
8% more quickly yeah that ought to by
now be standard practice for all
hospitals and yeah it's a continuing
frustration for me and I'm guessing for
you as well what's some of these
benefits is so obvious and we're still
stuck in a very very sort of slow slowly
evolving economic paradigm that's
reluctant to see at the bigger picture
because I'm sure maybe nobody has done
that kind of research yet but in a if
you have to go and work in a factory
assembly line environment if it feels a
bit more like a forest and a little less
like an inhumane machine that you've
just been plugged into and I'm sure that
a people will go there with a different
motivation probably work differently but
also most likely have less sick days and
and and actually be more efficient so it
very often once you dare to think more
holistically about these things then
there are health and economic benefits
that previously weren't figured into the
economics of it yeah absolutely so in
terms of the the Eden Project like what
is your thought on because right now
this post covered 19 a lot of talk about
maybe we should have in our move towards
globalizing and creating a globalised
supply system paid more attention to the
fact that certain things are actually
sensible to be able to supply to a
population at a more regional or local
level because you never know when there
might be a disruption to supply lines
and and so there's a lot more talk about
food sovereignty a lot more people going
back to growing food and and this these
technologies that enable that use either
artificial shells like the domes or
thermo flywheels with with water hot
water cool water storage that regulates
temperatures
for months rather than short-term em
these these artificial and slightly
artificial environments but but using
good physics and and not a lot of energy
to create the enabling conditions for
plants to grow that normally wouldn't
grow in that climate zone and under
those conditions where do you see those
technologies at what we've achieved so
far the potential that we could achieve
in the future and you think though if we
want to create a climate resilient world
where communities have food sovereignty
is might play a much bigger role in the
future a lot of strands to that question
I mean in some ways the most of one of
the most basic definitions of
architecture is about modifying the the
climates to create a more sort of
conducive internal environments and
there are some actually very good
examples of how that happens in biology
there's a plant called the Himalayan
rhubarb lives in there Himalayas and
it's a bit like an artificial greenhouse
it has these semi-transparent leaves and
it creates warmer conditions within its
underneath its leaves that allowed it to
become quite dominant and by far the
largest plants in its particular
ecosystem just just by modifying the
environment and slightly so I think
there's huge potential for creating
growing environments that improve our
food growing capabilities and yes there
is a very strong case for real
localizing or region release from
regionalizing and some of our our food
supply chains and I've met some people
who had a bridle at the idea of
localizing because it feels somehow
constraining but I think it's very
important to distinguish between
different types of resources and the way
I put it is that we need to localize our
physical resources and globalize our
intellectual
yeah it's not it's all about becoming
parochial is it's just sanity you know
read to share all the brilliant ideas
we've got and show how we can do that
with huge improvements in the efficiency
of the way we use resources and actually
applying the insights of systemic
biomimicry
to the redesign of the human impact on
earth and we've we've lost touch with
the biophysical realities of place and
region and if we want to fit back into
the global patterns you mentioned the
guy in patterns earlier if we want to
really be conscious responsible keystone
species in each ecosystem trying to
create conditions conducive to life
which is the Janine's wonderful one
one-liner of what does life do best and
if we need to pay more attention to
appropriate scale and in place and the
local ecosystem and then we can fit a
global whether we want to call it
civilization or not but we're gonna a
global species uniquely adapted through
each place into a biosphere but if we if
we try to do it
top-down it's it's it's not gonna work
we've lost we've lost the contact to the
biophysical realities and and need
global knowledge exchange and innovation
and solidarity to make this happen in
time to my mind yeah
recently I I was advising a national
government on the circular economy and
they asked me to try and describe you
know why is this important and the way I
presented to to them was well let's take
a lettuce just coming from the
supermarket let's see where that comes
from and the NPK nitrogen phosphorus and
potassium fertilizer that will have been
used to grow it
well the phosphorus would have probably
come from Morocco the nitrogen would
probably come from Qatar Joseon would
probably come from China those would
have all come together to the nearest
large food growing area which happened
to be Malaysia in this case and then it
would have been air freight the lettuce
but it'd have been air freighted from
Malaysia to where this particular
government was probably half of it would
have got wasted and then it would have
gone into incineration because they ran
out of landfill space and because of the
lettuce is 99% water that's a
ridiculously inefficient thing to do
and if you think of the molecules in
that lettuce they will traveled thirty
thousand kilometres and then they would
end up as ash it's just an absurd way of
doing things and such a long supply
chain it makes it nearly impossible to
achieve circularity so if you were to
take a more sensible approach and
localize that you could actually close
the loop on your a lot of your nutrient
cycles you could reduce the distance by
a factor of ten thousands of the
distance over which those molecules have
traveled
isn't that a much better way of doing
things with
they take advice I think we but it's
taken a long time for people to really
begin to see the systemic puzzle like
some some people seem to be more able to
think in patterns and systems than
others but I feel that Corbett 19
response has given many more people
everywhere in the world an embodied
lived experience of these kind of
systemic connections and the possibility
of changing at a global scale and and
and for me even ahead right now looks
like everybody is just bouncing back to
some sort of undesirable previous normal
and I feel that there things that play
now that that will make it much easier
to make people understand the importance
of that kind of redesign and and that
those kind of long supply lines are just
in in in an era where we're facing
potential climate Cataclysm if we don't
respond within the next 10 years and
it's just ludicrous and and you
personally because I just thinking about
climate I just remember that you
actually part of architects declare and
have been quite involved in building the
movement and last time we spoke you you
shared a little bit how quickly that
that grew
[Music]
yeah sure so in October November 2018
that was kind of pivotal moment for me
because I've been running my company for
about ten years and we've managed to get
certain things implemented but nowhere
near as many things as I hoped and the
most common reason I was given for
things not proceeding was that these
days great but the markets not ready for
this yet and they're the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate
Change issued their most alarming report
to date saying that you know unless we
achieve really radical reductions in the
next 10 years then frankly we're in deep
trouble and I thought well you know this
is insane how is it that on one hand are
being told in marketing already for this
and on the other hand the best
scientific advice in the world is
telling us that we're we're in deep
trouble so I reread one of my favorite
essays which is levels we've talked
about that before
Biden Meadows and it reminded me of how
to bring about change and in that essay
as you know but for the benefit of your
listeners and what she argues is that
there are different places to intervene
in a system and some of the things that
we think are often inferential are
actually well down her list of
priorities and right at the top is
changing the paradigm or mindset out of
which the system behavior emerges and so
I decided to do two things I started
work on a new book with Sarah Akaka
provisional title for that is paradigm
shifts for planetary emergency and then
I met up with an old friend of mine an
architect called Steve Tompkins for a
rather gloomy drinking the pub to talk
about what can we do about this and out
of that came the idea of getting a group
of architects together to make a joint
declaration and as time went on it
became obvious that the thing to do was
to make that a declaration of climate
University emergency
and that was because a number of other
organizations had started doing that so
a lot of local authorities that time
recently declared an emergency so we did
that and it was fantastic to see how
rapidly that was taken up so within the
first two days of launching we had 200
practices in the UK signed up to an 11
point declaration and those declaration
points they were also based on the idea
of paradigm shifts so really trying to
do something substantially different to
what we've been attempting for the last
30 years and we actually just passed the
one-year mock on the 30th of May that
was the one-year mark since we launched
just past 5,000 companies wide in 22
different countries so that's been
really energizing and exciting and we
holding in coordination meetings with
people in like 15 different time zones
sharing ideas how we can really make a
difference and what we're trying to do
is to use the kind of collective
influence and momentum of all these
signatories to bring about the kind of
tipping point that we need to make it
much easier to implement these things on
projects I from my own experience that
is really quite tough to try and achieve
the degree of system change and scale of
an individual project and by doing that
by getting all these people together and
use that collective influence we hope we
can bring back points here in the UK and
hopefully elsewhere as well how do you
see I mean that because all of those
architects those five dollars and firms
are caught and many of them I would
without wanting to offend them I'm not
as exploration and leading edges your
company is but they still also try to
push the boundaries and their fields and
they're still running to exactly the
wall you've described of
and wonderful ideas but the market isn't
quite ready for you for it yet and I get
the same conversations we've really
inspired leaders of larger
multinationals who really want to turn
the move into like they turn their
companies into regenerative companies if
they're privately owned they often have
quite a lot of leeway to do a lot of
things but if they're publicly owned
they actually very often stuck in a
system where the imagine of what they
can do is limited and so how do you see
a movement such as that actually
reaching into transforming the entire
building sector and and saying that I'm
immediately thinking of people like
Jason McClendon the living building
Institute or Jason twill I don't know
have you met him no he is he's another
person who worked a lot with the Living
Building Institute he's now in Australia
he's about to move to Dubai and he's for
many years been trying to transform not
as an architect but with the large
building constructing companies the
field of the built environment and who
do you see as allies in this systemic
transformation how do you make that link
from 5,000 firm saying we really would
like to do different practice and we we
need to shift the clients mmm there's
another question with so many strands to
it so one of the chapters that Sarah and
I working on in our book is about
maximization of agency and it seems to
be perhaps almost universal as a human
tendency to to minimize our agency and
think well I'm only an architect and
there's only a certain land I can do and
so I certainly see a lot of that even
amongst really quite senior influential
architects and
I see the same thing with companies who
say well you know weird answerable to
our shareholders and we have to deliver
good quickly returns and so on so
there's not much we can do and then I
see it from the media as well saying
well you know we have to create the
stories or programs that people will
watch and the advertisers will tolerate
and so on and and so it's this kind of
vicious cycle of agency minimization and
the more we do that the more it
encourages other people to minimize
their agency but the good news is is
that if you flip that the same is true
if we choose to maximize our agency in
half can have the same sort of viral
effects on others encouraging everyone
to to maximize their agency and and
that's what I see we need to do now when
we come up against some kind of obstacle
that's perhaps slightly higher up in the
chain of influence it's not enough to
just say well you know I've done as much
as I can we need to see how we can
overcome that obstacle as an example of
what I mean I gave a talk recently at a
conference about energy disruptors and
there was one of the very senior members
of shell they're saying well you know we
have to compete in a commercial
environment and I'm pushing I didn't get
a chance to speak to Marx but if I had
done I would have said to him we'll look
I think things have changed you know you
need to now change the commercial
environment you could perfectly well get
together with the four other major oil
companies and say look if we can run as
we are our kids will despise us for our
lack of courage you know because we knew
what was coming we need to change this
so if we work together we could actually
change their commercial environment and
I've heard from some people working in
the oil industry that there's a lot of
support for transformation within the
industry they want to see this
transformation and so you know coming
back to architects declare we're really
trying to encourage people to maximize
their agency and where that's difficult
to see how they can change things and
because now so many different
organizations
have declared a climate emergency
increasingly we're gonna find projects
where the architects the whole design
team the client organization and the
local authority planning department all
of them have declared a climate
emergency and that ought to be an
opportunity to really raise the level of
ambition and all work to see how you can
maximize the potential yeah and and
Lincoln with engineers declare and all
the other yes yeah well exactly so on in
the UK now we have architects structural
engineers to play civil engineers Claire
M&E engineers to player project managers
declare Landscape Architects to player
and then there's a separate organization
with I think 22 of the largest
developers who declare emergency so it's
definitely part of a growing movement it
reminds me of like last week of speaking
with people from Borland's and we
touched on how sometimes there's a real
discrepancy between the conversation you
can have with the individuals in in
companies if they if you talk to them as
individuals over the tea break or the
lunch and the roles people then play in
their professional environments and I in
that conversation I was reminded of a
situation that I had with a consultancy
client where that was really stuck to me
were working on a future exhibition of a
museum with a lot of bright people in
the room but the future that they were
projecting was a garish kind of sci-fi
future of everything done by technology
and then when you had conversations with
them and over the tea break and asked
them would you want your children to
grow up in that future there were a hell
no but-but-but-but in their professional
roles they felt that they were at their
brightest and most brigands they were
working for whatever space Asian
seasoned and large technological firms
and they just had to push this this
Technol dystopia as a techno utopia and
it wasn't what they actually wanted for
their own lives and in that experience I
came up with this I still haven't
written the essay the title for an essay
and values schizophrenia and I I feel
we're very often the professional roles
people are held in in the playing field
that is still rigged towards the
degenerative system you create this
value schizophrenia but where we and
that and reminds me of the famous
Buckminster Fuller quote in the end only
integrity is going to count so if if we
don't know all in all our professions
step into clearly saying I'm not gonna
be part of predatory delay anymore I'm
gonna speak to the real transformative
values that I actually hold when I think
of the future that I would like to
co-create and name these these these
idiosyncrasies inconsistencies but it's
it's it's a tricky one to do that and
still stay in a job wonderful to hear
that that there is so much movement now
in throughout the entire spectrum of the
built environment and is it is it mainly
uko do you feel that this is actually
popping up in lots of other countries
now as well I mean you said 22 countries
but is it that the buzzes mainly in the
UK with so-and-so declares or do you
find that it's big going global uh well
I mean they they're very active in
Australia and portions the size of
population they've got way more
signatures than we have ana de is also
really active and I'm just talking about
the architects declare and so on and
hey my impression is that there's quite
a lot going on in France moment as well
we wanted to be quite inspiring city
mayors like Anne Hidalgo and and so on
the Netherlands this is also pretty
active excellent so it is a globally
growing movement that's really good to
hear the there's a couple of things that
I'd still wanted to get to one one of
them is an update on what is happening
with the Sahara forest project because
like I included it in my book I still
use it in slideshows but I'm I think
I've seen that the prototype has been
built there isn't a physical
installation that runs yes we built a
prototype in Qatar that was open the
Emir of Qatar during their 2012 i'ma
change talks mmm and so that worked
extremely well we managed to grow
cucumbers throughout the summer with
half the amount of fresh water of
conventional approaches and we used that
opportunity to really test all the
different elements of the system and to
monitor the regenerative benefits and we
had hopes that we were going to be able
to go straight through to commercial
scale up in an but disappointing he odd
joint venture partner it was joint
venture with a Norwegian fertilizer
company and the Qatar fertilizer company
and the Norwegians were absolutely
delighted with its stake as a fertilizer
company decided it wasn't close enough
to their core business and so they
decided not to proceed which was
disappointing because you can't really
do anything in castle without a joint
venture katarina partner so after quite
a bit of work trying to find an
alternative there we we decided we were
gonna have to relocate that's to Jordan
so we built a version in Jordan that was
three times the size and that's des
operating
[Music]
they there was a deal with a company to
supply veg register and vegetables to
them so so you know it's is proceeding
and but it's still quite tough you know
it shouldn't be as difficult as this
really to realize projects like that and
that that's partly because there are a
lot of benefits that come out of a
present like that's secondary benefits
that aren't really accounted for in
conventional so you know we were eight
we've showed on the cat's-eye version we
were able to achieve a really
substantial regenerative benefit in
terms of the amount of plants and
animals that it returns to the sites and
we were able to stabilize things ground
sequester kind of a carbon into the
soils and so on and yeah most of those
things are quite difficult to monetize
return maybe but that's what you need to
do if you're to compete with a very sort
of hard commercial environment food
growing I mean in that particular case I
always felt that there for me when I saw
the involvement of the large fertilizer
companies and initially there was a
little bit of a alarm going off and then
I sort of thought of it in in the way
that I made sense of it for myself was
that at the scale that it was actually
envisioned of really bringing back micro
climates in it like restoring the
hydrological cycle by bringing back
trees around the coastal fringes of the
Sahara and using that that technology
then it's it's part of the transition to
use into external inputs to get it going
but well once it it's that establishes
itself it actually creates a cycle that
but is much more localized in terms of
nutrient flows and then you look and
into that part of it the the whole
exporting fertilizers to feed the system
like in
fertilizers to feed the system yeah sure
I'd recognize there are some tensions
there but the the couple didn't know
Asian company we were working with Yarra
they they kind of Rican sieved of their
company quite a few years ago now so
that it was no longer just about
manufacturing fertilizers they have
rebranded themselves as experts in crop
nutrition so they were very interested
in some of the approaches that we were
experimenting with that would use far
less synthetic fertilizer so looking at
biochar and even using seaweed to form
mechanic fertilizers in stolen and you
know for them their main interest was
that they they're concerned about the
growth of desertification and they see
potential for some use of fertilizers in
reversing desertification and we were we
were trying to lead them more in the
direction of organic fertilizers things
in that effort well that's that's so I'm
aligned with that kind of way of working
of saying sometimes you just have to
engage and you have to push people in
the process as you walk with them rather
than say no you're doing it wrong and
until you are perfect don't talk to me
but it is always a fine line to decide
where where to have that sort of weird
still incremental improvements but
possibly incremental improvements that
then create the conditions for
transformative change for an entire
industry to happen and in that place we
need these these imperfect but catalytic
projects well that's exactly yes yeah
I've occasionally worked with companies
that have a poor historical record and
makes the difference for me whether I
will work with them or not is whether
I'm convinced that they are really
committed to transformative change if
they are then happy to work with them
this census if if I don't think they're
really committed and they're just doing
it for Anna greenwashing then sorry it's
not gonna get involved
before we end because you mentioned a
side sentence the book you're writing
with Sarah I would love to you both your
first book biomimicry an architecture
and the book you're writing right now
tell me a little bit more about those
books sure so I'm in McLean architecture
I was commissioned to write that by the
our apiary the Royal Institute of
British Architects and that was such a
pleasure you know it's like forcing
myself to write a detailed manifesto for
what I want to do with my company
getting to meet and talk to a lot of the
best experts from around the world so
that was a really useful process for me
and this new one well with we're still
in the writing process at the moment so
not sure when it's going to be published
but each chapter is going to be
describing a paradigm shift so the first
one is about shift from sustainable to
regenerative and then we're going to go
on to looking at how we need to
radically transform our view of the rest
of the living world and this is picking
up on some of the work from
philosophically freya Matthews and also
Jeremy Lent I particularly enjoyed his
book instincts in which she's Sheridan
if we carry on with a metaphor of nature
something to be conquered then we sit
there as trouble and we need to
transform that as so that we see
ourselves as part of a web of life
support systems and you need to
integrate yourselves insulin then we'll
go on to to talk but transforming cities
and rethinking our relationship with
time and trying to think over longer
time scales and we'll be looking at the
whole issue of sort of growth and D
growth and our arguments will be that
what we need to head for is is actually
a state of dynamic equilibrium
so I'm not convinced by the framing of
the D growth pieces I think a lot of
saying is great but the framing is
problematic and I think it's it's much
more likely to succeed if we talk about
dynamic equilibrium dad does you have in
biology systems with high levels of
growth decay and renewal existing
balance and then we finished the book
with a chapter about agency so this is
about neither being impossible sorry
neither being an optimist or a pessimist
but instead being a possible issed that
maximizes their agency yes so those six
paradigm shifts we see is as crucial to
really addressing the stain of emotions
have you come across the quite a few
years back I think it was in 2009 and
Hazel Henderson and Fritjof Capra got
commissioned by I think it was the
British Institute for Chartered
Accountants or something like that and
to write a in internal like a sort of
monograph and that was called
qualitative growth and they in it they
distinguished again because I have the
same sort of as a biologist and
ecologist and Earth System scientists I
feel uncomfortable with notions of
growth is bad and D growth but then of
course I understand enough about the the
dysfunctionality of the current economic
system and monetary system that I know
that that kind of growth is impossible
and and so so for me it's not it's about
redeeming growth as a word so it doesn't
become a dirty word and by putting this
qualitative growth in you you actually
make like in in nature you things start
growing exponentially normally
populations and then eventually they
have that inflection point and they
shift from the logistic from the
exponential curve to the logistic curve
and and once they do that past the
inflection point the the journey is a
qualitative
like Justin you in our lines we stopped
growing in terms of dimensions some time
ago but but then then you learn stuff
and you build relationships and you you
build tacit knowledge and experience and
that's the qualitative growth and I feel
it fits well with with dynamic
equilibrium which almost even more like
bringing in the the adaptive cycle of
ecosystems change reminds us that there
will be phases where it's rapid growth
and there will be phases where it's the
dissolution of structures and and
negative growth but overall you need to
keep them in an equilibrium and the
buffer is through the panarchy that they
it happens at different scales in
different places at the same time and
then overall you create the equilibrium
I mean that's at least how our natural
systems work oh yes well you you write
about it very eloquently in your book
and yes I'm with you on that so
wonderful and this has been been a joy
to explore and I hope we have more
opportunities to work together and
explore put putting our years together
and also into practice let's see what we
can dream up here on my yoga because I'm
increasingly wanting to create projects
where I live but I still sensed it
there's a huge opportunity to work with
islands as models for by a regional
change and a lot of these whether we're
talking cities like like habit JIRA they
wrote this lovely book on on
regenerative cities and friend of mine
alone through the Finland fellows and
and again what he pointed out very early
on when he did the footprint of London
is is that if you want to transform
cities you have to transform them within
their region and we don't have good
models of that yet but my hope here at
the moment this is an invitation for
faster to collaborate is is that here in
Majorca
having had a real shock to the main
industry through all that 19 that I
think sits deep enough that now people
will hear the warning that I've been
giving for 10 years of well you need to
prepare for the times when tourism isn't
as strong anymore now so you pray you're
ready when the contraction happens
rather than try to maximize profits
until the very last moment and I think
that's that's arrived in people and
there's a real possibility to explore
how to turn a half a million people city
in a million people region into in turn
new direction islands are interesting
because it's very obvious where the
physical limits are that's not always so
clear with River City it's part of a
larger region so so yeah and you'll be
in a pleasure to to work with you on
something and thank you so much for
involving me in this town you great
wonderful just